<file name="Html02Intro" title="Introduction to HTML" toc="HtmlIntroTOC">
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS01.jpg" alt="First HTML CSS Image"/>
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS02.jpg" alt="Second HTML CSS Image"/>
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS03.jpg" alt="Third HTML CSS Image"/>
    <br/>

    <bullet>
        HTML stands for <b>HyperText Markup Language</b>, and it is the language of the web.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        When you view a page on the web, your web browser processes the HTML, along with styling information, into
        the page you see on your screen.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        Even if the website was written using PHP, Ruby, Python, or Java the final result that your browser sees
        is just HTML.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        HyperText is described as text that is displayed on an electronic device that can be linked to other text
        which is accessible to the user.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        Whenever you click on a link on a web page, you are taking advantage of HyperText linking.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        A Markup Language is defined annotations that gets added to text that describes the text further.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        In this course, we will be using HTML5, the fifth revision of the HTML standard.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <h2>MINI LAB</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>What is HTML?</li>
            <li>What is HyperText?</li>
            <li>What is a markup language?</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <div id="doctype"></div>
    <h3 class="subTitle">Doctype Declaration</h3>

    <bullet>
        The first line of an HTML document is the doctype declaration. Since there are different versions of the
        HTML standard, this line is needed to help the browser identify the data that will follow.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        For HTML5, the doctype declaration looks like this:<br/>
        <text>|||lt!DOCTYPE html></text>
    </bullet>

    <div id="root"></div>
    <h3 class="subTitle">Root Element</h3>

    <bullet>
        In an element-based markup language, the root element is the first element on the page. It is also the
        element that contains all other elements. For HTML, the root element is <b>|||lthtml></b>.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        So far, this is what we have:<br/>
        <text>
            |||lt!DOCTYPE html>
            |||lthtml>
            |||lt/html>
        </text>
    </bullet>

    <div id="head_and_body"></div>
    <h3 class="subTitle">Head and Body</h3>

    <bullet>
        Within the root element, <b>|||lthtml></b>, of an html document, you will find a <b>|||lthead></b> element,
        and a <b>|||ltbody></b> element. The <b>|||lthead></b> element is used to tell the web browser information
        about the web page. The <b>|||ltbody></b> element is used to define the content that the web browser will
        display to a user.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Now, we have a document that looks like this:<br/>
        <text tid="t1"></text>
    </bullet>

    <div id="page_title"></div>
    <h4 style="margin-left: 50px;;">Page Title</h4>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        As you know, web pages have titles. You have seen these in the title bar of your web browser, or in the name
        of bookmarks you make. There is an element, <b>|||lttitle></b>, that gets added to the HTML document's
        <b>|||lthead></b> that provides the title to the web browser. An HTML document with a title looks like this:
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <text tid="t2"></text>
    </bullet>

    <div id="metadata"></div>
    <h4 style="margin-left: 50px;;">Metadata</h4>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Metadata, or extended information, can be provided via the |||ltmeta> element within the document's
        |||lthead>. A few examples of things specified via metadata are:<br/>
        <ul>
            <li>search keywords</li>
            <li>page description</li>
            <li>page author</li>
            <li>page character set</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <b>Example:</b>
        <text tid="t3"></text>
        Notice that there is no close tag for <b>|||ltmeta></b> because it is a void element.
    </bullet>

    <div id="styles"></div>
    <h4 style="margin-left: 50px;;">Styles and Scripts</h4>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Later on, we will learn about adding styles and scripts to our HTML pages. There are special elements that get
        added to the document to describe such data that we will discuss in more detail in a later section.
    </bullet>

    <div id="comments"></div>
    <h4 style="margin-left: 50px;;">Comments</h4>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Comments in HTML pages look different from what you see in PHP or other programming languages. HTML comments
        will not be rendered by the web browser, but are viewable in the source of the web page. An HTML comment
        looks like this:
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <text tid="t4"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <h2>MINI LAB 02</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>What version of HTML are we using?</li>
            <li>What tag specifies that version?</li>
            <li>Which tag is the root element?</li>
            <li>Which element of the page has the title and the meta data?</li>
            <li>Which element of the page has the information which the web browser will display?</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <div id="markup"></div>
    <h3 class="subTitle">Semantic Markup</h3>

    <bullet>
        As we get further into HTML and begin learning about some of the available elements, you may notice that the
        same visual result can be achieved using different combinations of markup and styles. It should be noted that
        the HTML element that best describes the data that it contains is the appropriate one for the job.<br/>

        Keep in mind that there are other consumers of web pages besides web browsers. For example, there are screen
        readers, for the visually impaired, that actually read the contents of the page to a user. If you do not use
        the appropriate elements to hold your data, the screen reader will not provide a good user experience.
    </bullet>

    <div id="review"></div>
    <h3 class="subTitle">HTML Introduction Review</h3>

    <bullet>
        What is HTML?
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The language of the web. (HyperText Markup Language)
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        What is HyperText?
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Text displayed on an electronic device that can be linked to other text accessible to the user.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        What is a markup language?
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        A type of document with defined annotations that determines how other text is displayed.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>What version of HTML are we using?</bullet>
    <bullet indent="indent-star">HTML 5</bullet>

    <bullet>What tag specifies that version?</bullet>
    <bullet indent="indent-star"><text>|||lt!DOCTYPE html></text></bullet>

    <bullet>Which tag is the root element?</bullet>
    <bullet indent="indent-star"><text>|||lthtml></text></bullet>

    <bullet>Which element of the page has the title and the meta data</bullet>
    <bullet indent="indent-star">|||lthead></bullet>

    <bullet>Which element of the page has the information which the web browser will display?</bullet>
    <bullet indent="indent-star">|||ltbody></bullet>

    <bullet>What are two reasons for using Semantic based html tags?</bullet>
    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <ul>
            <li>They provide a better user interface for screen readers.</li>
            <li>They make the intent of the code more clear to programmers reading the code.</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <a href="https://java.codeup.com/html-css/introduction/#exercises" class="btn btn-info" Target="blank">
        HTML Introduction Exercises</a>
</file>