<file name="CSS01/Css1_01Introduction" title="Introduction to CSS " toc="Css1_01IntroTOC">
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS01.jpg" alt="First HTML CSS Image"/>
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS02.jpg" alt="Second HTML CSS Image"/>
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS03.jpg" alt="Third HTML CSS Image"/>
    <br/>

    <h1 id="css_overview">CSS Overview</h1>

    <p>CSS stands for Cascading Style Sheets. CSS describes how HTML elements are to be displayed on screen.</p>

    <bullet>
        In this section, we will learn the basics of CSS, including basic styling, the box model, and different types
        of positioning.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        CSS also provides for the separation of the document content from the presentation. This separation has many
        benefits, including:
        <ul>
            <li>Content can be used independently of styling for other purposes.</li>
            <li>Styles can be re-used across pages.</li>
            <li>Updating styles in a stylesheet that is used in many pages is much more efficient than updating
                all the pages individually.</li>
            <li>Bandwidth savings can be significant due to stylesheet caching.</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

    <bullet>
        In this lesson, we will cover three different ways to apply css styles to our web pages;
        <ul>
            <li>using the style attribute</li>
            <li>using an embedded (inline) stylesheet</li>
            <li>using an external stylesheet</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="attribute">Element Style Attribute</h2>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        One of the simplest ways to add style to an HTML element is by using the <b>style</b> attribute.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <b>Example:</b><br/>
        <text tid="t1"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        This is also the least recommended method, because all the benefits described in the overview do not
        apply to styles applied in this way. Nonetheless, it is still useful to test a style quickly, or for a one-off
        style change, or for a quick demonstration. I often use this method in the class for demonstrations.
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="inline">Inline/Embedded Stylesheet</h2>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Another method of adding styles to a webpage is via an embedded stylesheet. This can be accomplished by
        using a <b>style</b> element in the <b>head</b> of your HTML page.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <b>Example:</b><br/>
        <text tid="t2"></text><br/>
        Using styles in this way provides some of the benefits described in the overview, but not all of them.
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="external">External Stylesheet</h2>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Finally, another way to add styles to a web page is to link to an external stylesheet. This is the
        recommended method, and the one that will provide all of the benefits listed in the overview.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <b>From Stylesheet:</b><br/>
        <text tid="t3"></text><br/>
        <b>From HTML:</b><br/>
        <text tid="t4"></text><br/>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Using this method, the <i>fancy-header</i> style can be used multiple times in multiple pages. If you want
        to change what a <i>fancy-header</i> looks like, you only need to change it in one place and the update
        will take place anywhere it is used.
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="comments">Comments</h2>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Comments in CSS are started with a slash followed by an asterisk (<hl>/*</hl>), and ended with the same
        in reverse order, (<hl>*/</hl>).
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <b>Example:</b><br/>
        <text tid="t5"></text><br/>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="review">Review</h2>

    <bullet>
        What does CSS stand for?
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Cascading Style Sheets
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        What are the advantages of separating the document content from the presentation style?
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <ul>
            <li>Content can be used independently of styling for other purposes.</li>
            <li>Styles can be re-used across pages.</li>
            <li>Updating styles in a stylesheet that is used in many pages is much more efficient than updating
                all the pages individually.</li>
            <li>Bandwidth savings can be significant due to stylesheet caching.</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        What are the three ways to apply styles to a website?
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <ul>
            <li>using the style attribute</li>
            <li>using an embedded (inline) stylesheet</li>
            <li>using an external stylesheet</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        Which method best supports the advantages of separating styling from content?
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        using an external stylesheet
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        How do we add a comment into a stylesheet?
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Comments in CSS are started with a slash followed by an asterisk (<hl>/*</hl>), and ended with the same
        in reverse order, (<hl>*/</hl>).
    </bullet>

    <br/>
    <a href="https://java.codeup.com/html-css/css-i/introduction/#exercises" class="btn btn-info" Target="blank">
        Exercises</a>
</file>