<file name="CSS01/Css1_02Selectors" title="CSS Selectors and Properties" toc="Css1_02SelectorsTOC">
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS01.jpg" alt="First HTML CSS Image"/>
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS02.jpg" alt="Second HTML CSS Image"/>
    <img class="md-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS03.jpg" alt="Third HTML CSS Image"/>
    <br/>

    <br/>
    <p  id="home">In this lesson, we will talk about how to use CSS selectors and a few different CSS properties.</p>

    <h2>CSS Selectors</h2>

    <bullet>
        One of the keys to styling HTML documents is being able to selectively apply styles to specific elements
        or groups of elements. In order to do this, something called a <b>CSS selector</b> is used.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        A CSS selector is the part of a CSS rule set that actually selects the content you want to style.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        There are many types of CSS selectors, and advanced selectors can get quite complicated. We will be teaching
        you the basics so that you can start adding your own style to your pages.
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="basic_selectors">Basic Selectors</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Lets take a look at a template for basic selector:<br/>
        <text tid="t1"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <ul>
            <li>A style definition starts with a selector. </li>
            <li>Following the selector is an open and a close curly brace.</li>
            <li>Inside the curly braces is a list of key:value pairs.</li>
            <li>As we saw in the last lesson, the key:value pairs have a colon between them, and a semi-colon after them. </li>
            <li>The key is the name of a CSS property, and the value is the value of the property is being used.</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Example:<br/>
        <text tid="t2"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <b>Rules for the selector:</b><br/>
        <img class="lg-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS04.png" alt="Third HTML CSS Image"/>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Two more examples:<br/>
        <text tid="t3"></text>
        <text tid="t4"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="multiple_selectors">Multiple Selectors</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        If you would like to have multiple selectors have the same style definition, you can separate the
        selectors with commas as follows:<br/>
        <text tid="t5"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Example:<br/>
        <text tid="t6"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="combining_classes">Combining Classes</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Often times, you want an HTML element to have several style classes applied. That can be accomplished as
        follows:<br/>
        <text tid="t7"></text>
        <text tid="t8"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="descendent_selectors">Descendent Selector</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Often times, it is useful to apply style to an element or group of elements based on their descendant
        relationship to some parent element in the page.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        To create a descendent selector, you first type the parent selector, followed by a space, followed by the
        descendent selector.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <text tid="t9"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        In this example, any <b>h1</b> elements that are a descendant of the element with the id of <b>container</b>
        will be blue. Other <b>h1</b> elements that are not a descendant of an element with <b>id="container"</b>
        will not receive the style.
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="child_selectors">Direct-Child Selector</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The direct child selector is similar to the descendent selector except that only direct children
        of the parent selector will receive the specified style. For the direct-child selector a greater
        than symbol, <hl>|||gt</hl>, is used in place of the space from the descendent selector.<br/>
        <text tid="t10"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="combining_selectors">Combining Selectors</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Sometimes it is useful to combine selectors to be more specific. For example, if the <b>fancy-header</b>
        class is only applicable to <b>h1</b> elements, then it can be written as follows:<br/>
        <text tid="t11"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        In the example above, <b>h1</b> elements with <b>class="fancy-header"</b> will receive the specified style, but
        other element types with <b>class="fancy-header"</b> will not.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Combination selectors also allow for customization of properties based on element type. For example:<br/>
        <text tid="t12"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        In this example, you can see that <b>h1</b> and <b>h2</b> elements will receive different styling through
        the use of the same class name. Combination of id selectors is not recommended since it might lose the
        uniqueness purpose of the id selector.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        <h2>MINI LAB</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>What is a <b>CSS Selector</b>?</li>
            <li>List three things that can be selectors.</li>
            <li>How can you have multiple selectors for one style definition?</li>
            <li>Can an element have more than one class?</li>
            <li>What is the difference between a <b>Descendent Selector</b> and a <b>Direct-Child Selector</b>?</li>
            <li>How do you make a class apply only to one element?</li>
            <li>Create a web page with a corresponding CSS file.</li>
            <li>In the CSS file, create a class named "danger" that sets <b>color</b> to "red"</li>
            <li>In the web page, create a paragraph using the danger class that says, "Danger Zone".</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="pseudo_classes">Pseudo Classes</h2>

    <bullet>
        Pseudo classes can be added to a selector to specify that a particular style should be applied only to a
        particular state of an element.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        First, let us see the syntax for a pseudo class with a selector:<br/>
        <text tid="t13"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        Notice the colon after the selector, followed by the pseudo-class name. There are many pseudo-classes
        available in CSS and some of the most commonly used deal with the anchor element.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        Examples:<br/>
        <text tid="t14"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        As you can see, pseudo-classes allow us to style the anchor element based on different states of
        the link. For a more complete list of available pseudo-classes, look at the
        <span class="green">Mozilla Developer Network</span>.
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="specificity">Specificity</h2>

    <bullet>
        Due to the cascading nature of style sheets, and the potential for duplicate or conflicting styles being
        applied to an element, there must be a set of rules that determine what styles actually get applied.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        The process of deciding what styles get applied is referred to as <b>specificity</b>. In general, the more
        specific the selector, the higher the precedence, the more likely the style will be applied.
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="colors">Colors</h2>

    <bullet>
        How do colors work on CSS?
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        One way to reference a color is simply by using its name. For example, <b>red</b> or <b>blue</b> are valid
        colors in CSS.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        Another way to reference a color is by using its RGB value, and this is the preferred method. As you may have
        guessed, RGB stands for Red/Green/Blue.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        RGB values can be specified in CSS in several ways:<br/>
        <ul>
            <li>"#FFFFFF", this is white</li>
            <li>"#F00", this is red</li>
            <li>"rgb(200, 200, 200)", this is grayish</li>
            <li>"rgba(0, 0, 255, 0.5)", this is a dark blue</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        The most common method is by using a six character hexadecimal value.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        You now know that colors can be specified using a six character hexadecimal value that represents the RGB
        value of a color. This implies that there are two hex characters for each color. Based on that knowledge,
        let us look at some example colors:<br/>
        <text tid="t15"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        From the examples above, along with some knowledge of the hexadecimal number system, you can begin to see
        how hex color codes work. We can also see that since 00-FF represents 256 unique values, we have a total
        of 256 x 256 x 256 (over 16 million) color combinations.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        Besides seeing six character hex color codes, you may also see three character hex color codes. Three
        character color codes are a shorthand notation that works as follows:<br/>
        <text tid="t16"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        <h2>MINI LAB 02</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>What is the process of deciding what styles get applied called?</li>
            <li>What color is #00ff00?</li>
            <li>In your stylesheet, set the DIV elements to change the background color to "#00ff00" when you hover them.</li>
            <li>Add a paragraph with text to the div</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="common_properties">Common CSS Properties and Values</h2>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="color">color</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The CSS <b>color</b> property sets the foreground color of an element's text content and its decorations.
        It does not affect any other characteristic of the element.<br/>
        <text tid="t17"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="text_decoration">text-decoration</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>text-decoration</b> CSS property is used to set the text formatting to underline, overline,
        line-through, or blink.<br/>
        <text tid="t18"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="text_align">text-align</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>text-align</b> CSS property describes how inline content like text is aligned in its parent block
        element. text-align does not control the alignment of block elements itself, only their inline content.<br/>
        <text tid="t19"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="text_indent">text-indent</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>text-indent</b> CSS property specifies how much horizontal space should be left before the beginning
        of the first line of the text content of an element. Horizontal spacing is with respect to the left
        (or right, for right-to-left layout) edge of the containing block element's box. <br/>
        <text tid="t20"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="font_properties">Font Properties</h2>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="font_family">font-family</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>font-family</b> CSS property allows for a prioritized list of font family names and/or generic family
        names to be specified for the selected element.
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Unlike most other CSS properties, values are separated by a comma to indicate that they are alternatives.
        The browser will select the first font on the list that is installed on the computer or that can be downloaded
        using the information provided by a @font-face at-rule.<br/>
        <text tid="t21"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>font-family</b> CSS property allows for a prioritized list of font family names and/or generic family
        names to be specified for the selected element. You may be curious what the difference is between a serif font,
        and a sans-serif font. Serifs are the fancy edges/lines that appear on the end of characters. Serif fonts have
        the fancy edges, sans-serif fonts are "without" serifs. <br/>
        <img class="lg-img" src="resource/images/HTMLandCSS05.png" alt="Fifth HTML CSS Image"/><br/>
        Monospace fonts are a bit different in that all the characters are the same width. Monospace fonts are often
        used in terminals to help with readability. <br/>
        <br/>
        More information on font families can be found on the MDN.
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="font_style">font-style</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>font-style</b> CSS property allows italic or oblique faces to be selected within a font-family.<br/>
        <text tid="t22"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="font_size">font-size</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>font-size</b> CSS property specifies the size of the font – specifically the desired height of
        glyphs from the font. Setting the font size may, in turn, change the size of other items since it is used
        to compute the value of em and ex length units.<br/>
        <text tid="t23"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        As you can see in the examples above, different units can be used to specify sizes in CSS. Here is a
        description of the units used above:<br/>
        <ul>
            <li><b>px</b> stands for pixels. Pixels are an absolute unit used for screen media.</li>
            <li><b>em</b> is a relative/dynamic unit that corresponds to the current font size. If the current font
                size is 12px, then 1em is 12px. 2em would be 24px. 0.5 em would be 6px. If the browser font size
                changes, all em values would change accordingly.</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        <b>Here is a note regarding pixels from the MDN:</b><br/>
        Note: Defining font sizes in pixel is not accessible, because the user cannot change the font size
        from the browser. (For example, users with limited vision may wish to set the font size much larger
        than the size chosen by a web designer.) Therefore, avoid using pixels for font sizes if you wish to
        create an inclusive design.
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="font_weight">font-weight</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>font-weight</b> CSS property specifies the weight or boldness of the font. However, some fonts are
        not available in all weights; some are available only on normal and bold.<br/>
        <text tid="t24"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        <h2>MINI LAB 03</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>Which property sets the text color?</li>
            <li>How do we left justify text?</li>
            <li>How do you separate alternative font families?</li>
            <li>What is wrong with using pixels to set the font size?</li>
            <li>In your stylesheet, create a class named right-just with right justified text and a font size of 3em;</li>
            <li>Set the font family of the text to "Times New Roman" or Times or Serif.</li>
            <li>Use the new class on the paragraph in your DIV.</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="background_properties">Background Properties</h2>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="background_color">background-color</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>background-color</b> CSS property sets the background color of an element, either through a color
        value or the keyword transparent.<br/>
        <text tid="t25"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="background_image">background-image</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The CSS <b>background-image</b> property sets one or several background images for an element. The images are
        drawn on successive stacking context layers, with the first specified being drawn as if it is the closest
        to the user.<br/>
        <text tid="t26"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="background_repeat">background-repeat</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>background-repeat</b> CSS property defines how background images are repeated. A background image
        can be repeated along the horizontal axis, the vertical axis, both, or not repeated at all.<br/>
        <text tid="t27"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h3 class="subPoint" id="list_style">list-style</h3>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The <b>list-style</b> CSS property is a shorthand property for setting list-style-type, list-style-image,
        and list-style-position.<br/>
        <text tid="t28"></text>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="inheriting_styles">Inheriting Styles</h2>

    <bullet>
        The <b>inherit</b> CSS-value causes the element for which it is specified to take the computed
        value of the property from its parent element. It is allowed on every CSS property.<br/>
        <text tid="t29"></text>
    </bullet>

    <bullet>
        <h2>MINI LAB 04</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>How do you override a set attribute with a parent attribute?</li>
            <li>In your CSS file, set the paragraph color to #0000ff.</li>
            <li>On your web page, add the danger class to you DIV</li>
            <li>Add a second paragraph to you DIV with the id set to "override".</li>
            <li>Add some text to the second paragraph.</li>
            <li>In your CSS file, set any paragraph with the id "override" to inherit it's color from it's parent.</li>
        </ul>
    </bullet>

    <h2 id="review">Review</h2>

    <bullet>What is a <b>CSS Selector</b>?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        A CSS selector is the part of a CSS rule set that actually selects the content you want to style.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>List three things that can be selectors.</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">Elements, IDs, and Classes</bullet>

    <bullet>How can you have multiple selectors for one style definition?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">You can separate the selectors with commas.</bullet>

    <bullet>Can an element have more than one class?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">Yes</bullet>

    <bullet>What is the difference between a <b>Descendent Selector</b> and a <b>Direct-Child Selector</b>?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        The direct child selector is similar to the descendent selector except that only direct children of the parent
        selector will receive the specified style.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>How do you make a class apply only to one element?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">Append the class name to the element name with a period.</bullet>

    <bullet>How do you specify to use a Pseudo Class?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">Append the Pseudo Class name to the element name with a colon.</bullet>

    <bullet>What is the process of deciding what styles get applied called?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">Specificity</bullet>

    <bullet>What color is #00ff00?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">Green</bullet>

    <bullet>Which property sets the text color?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">color</bullet>

    <bullet>How do we left justify text?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">Use the text-align property. (text-align: left;)</bullet>

    <bullet>How do you separate alternative font families?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">With commas (<i>element { font-family: Helvetica, Arial, Sans-Serif; }</i>)</bullet>

    <bullet>What is wrong with using pixels to set the font size?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">
        Defining font sizes in pixel is not accessible, because the user cannot change the font size from the browser.
    </bullet>

    <bullet>How do you override a set attribute with a parent attribute?</bullet>

    <bullet indent="indent-star">Set the attribute to "inherit" (color: inherit;)</bullet>

    <br/>
    <a href="https://java.codeup.com/html-css/css-i/selectors-and-properties/#further-reading" class="btn btn-info" Target="blank">
        Further Reading and Exercises</a>
</file>